<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
     <string name="en_taivas_niklas_hed">"
TOWARDS ON THE DEAD HARD DUNA

˝Because you stop playing that stupid thing.˝
Mom has asked it so many times that itˊs no longer a question. Pointless. Niklas doesnˊt answer. He plays. He plays the devil because itˊs a) cool and b) his job.
Niklas Hed is one of the three founders of Rovio. He played a key role in the creation of AngryBirds, and therefore knows the stunt dna better than anyone else. Hed consumes a lot of entertainment products to understand what the competitors are doing and what they can do next. He knows that every human being has a small child and that we want games that are easy first and then deep.
He knows us well, but we donˊt know him at all. Hed does not rotate, does not chat and usually does not respond to emails. Heˊs not a hermit, but he doesnˊt have time for media interviews. He would rather have fun or do some fun with his family.
The superstar of the gaming world is not recognized when he opens the door of his Volvo XC60 and slips with his three-year-old son into a shopping mall in Espoo. There are thousands of such Volvo cars in Finland. Nobody bothers when he jumps on a boat and drives to fish off Keilaniemi. Itˊs one of those moments when Niklas Hed smiles. The snare swings. Next to it is the western fairway.
The worst may now be behind.
In the past, Hed was much more busy; when he was Rovioˊs chief of operations. Co-workers could interrupt the man five times on the way from the office to the garage. The rush has now been delegated to Harri Koponen, the sonera of the past few years, hired to succeed Hed. Hed can now focus on games. He asked about Koponenˊs news after he had been in the house for a month.
˝I havenˊt even had time to go cunt,˝ Koponen grinned and leapt forward, panting.
+
Niklas Hed realized the importance of a great deal of work at a young age in competitive sports. Cutting one tithe required a crazy rumble, and the whole duel could go down the toilet if the swimmer got sore before the race.
The Hedi lived in Nummela at that time. Niklas followed the practice of Jani Sievinen admiringly. The multiple world champion in swimming set an example and revealed to others the opportunities that diligence can open up. Sievinen did not tape on any of the workouts. Hed will never forget the attitude of his role model, even though he himself did not become a top swimmer.

˝I can learn anything if Iˊm interested, ˝Hed says. ˝But if Iˊm not interested, itˊs really hard for me to do anything about it. Iˊm super lazy, if not to snatch. I delegate things very quickly to those who might enjoy them more. ˝
While working out at the Nummela Swimming Pool, Niklas Hed first wondered why he would go big, sport or nerd. The swimmer began to lean over the nerdy line as his shoulder slipped out of place. It didnˊt want to stay in the pit after that.
Hedˊs mother was a clothing entrepreneur. The boy liked that his mother worked at home and was there every time he came from school. But she didnˊt like how hard her mother had to work in the high season, under Christmas and the cap. Niklas told his mother very clearly that he would never become an entrepreneur. However, his mind changed during his studies.
˝I realized it was the surest way to get things done so I could do cool things.˝
Niklas Hed has regretted his choice for one microsecond. At the time, the stall had a bad money shortage and had to fire twenty people. Many had become his friends and many were very good at his job. But:
˝You leave. You stay. You leave.˝
In 2012, the painful memories are almost forgotten. Rovio is a sensation. Angry Birds have been downloaded in different versions over a billion times. Rovioˊs main owners, cousins Niklas and Mikael Hed, and the father of the latter, Kaj, have succeeded in building Rovioˊs right company, backed by marketing director Peter Vesterbacka, ready to go public and grow very large. The headquarters in Keilaranta, Espoo, now employ more than 500 people.
According to Niklas Hed, Rovioˊs success is not based on luck but on a ˝wickedly hard dune˝. Before the breakthrough of Angry Birds, Hed and his friends made dozens of big mistakes and thousands of little ones.
˝Thatˊs what you learn when you do. You must take them by the heel. This house is built on a swamp, damn it.˝
Another way is to focus your thoughts on opportunities. In Rovio, this kind of thinking has led to startling powers in creating a new one. According to Hed, the company has found methods to produce ten times the number of ideas from the same group. An hourˊs brainstorm is enough. During this, ten new game ideas can be created if the team relies on intuition and focuses on the things that light up.
According to Hed, Rovioˊs leading characters are very common types - maybe just a little harder, more ambitious and more stubborn. Strong personalities organize heated and entertaining debates that do not immediately lead to a decision. The owners challenge each other, but they quickly settle. There is no time for a long rant.
˝The next match is about to begin.ˊ
+
Rovioˊs first installment was very, very modest.
Niklas Hed, who started his studies at the University of Technology, and his friends Jarno Väkeväinen and Kim Dikert, entered and won a Nokia and HP-sponsored mobile game competition. The year was 2003 and the name of the game was King ofthe Cabbage World It was a real-time multiplayer game whose heroes were explosive moles.

A Relude company was formed around the mole game, which was started by three shareholders. Each injected three tons of seed capital into Relude. Studying was missed because Relude provided a much more exciting experience.
Mikael Hed joined the company in 2005, and his father Kaj a year later. Kaj Hed invested one million euros in the company, not because of his son or nephew, but because he saw an opportunity based on the explosive growth of mobile devices. The company hired 30 employees. The name was changed to Rovio Mobile.
However, the enthusiasm for capital injection and new people quickly subsided.
Rovioˊs games received good reviews, but commercially the projects were disappointing. Rovio also subcontracted to Nokia and gaming giants Electronic Arts and Vivend, but in these projects the subscribers won at the expense of the supplier.
˝I remember when we localized a Nokia game to 67 languages, ˝says Niklas Hed. ˝For Arabia, I was going to shoot myself. Afterwards, I heard that Nokia had a team of about twenty people specializing in Arabic.˝
The Heds could not let go of poor quality even though they should have. The profitability of the projects suffered due to ambition. Budgets were disappointing. The company made cod, consumed more than it produced. The impatient guys left.
In the first decade of the 21st century, small arcades were ridiculous pieces in a big game dominated by telecom operators. Game companies went hand in hand to talk to the operators. Great buyers behaved like idiots.

˝Of course they had to be damn good. He had to lick the gatekeepers ass, romp with them and drink. Basically, it was pretty easy. But the problem was that there were so many of them. There were 200 of them. ˝
The industryˊs ecosystem was sick. Operators insisted that the games run on all possible devices (2,000) and ramped up 70% of the game revenue. It was only a matter of time before such a system collapsed. The frustrated Hedi came to their own conclusions and opted for a so-called square strategy. Rovio went to sleep. The company shrank to a minimum of 12 people.
Then came Apple and offered a model that was like paradise. Apple would think of everything, take care of everything, and charge only a 30 percent commission. All obstacles were minimized right out of the box. No more secret handshakes, no sauna evenings, no more drinking. All they needed was the best products and the skill to market them. But the competition would be crazy: a hundred thousand applications.
Rovio saw the opportunity. It chose a strategy of super-efficiency. The Heds decided to develop 12-15 games, spend 25-40,000 euros each and see what would fly. Angry Birds was the first in the series. However, the budget for the game was disappointing: 50,000 euros had already been burned and did not seem like a decent game.
˝The feel was not good, ˝Hed says. [OF,
The catfish slings had to be tweaked, adjusted. The bundles of birds, pigs and rocks were analyzed with the utmost precision to adjust the coefficients of elasticity. At first, the Angry Birds also twitch. The demo phaseˊs three frames per second was finally accelerated to 30 frames, ensuring perfect smooth motion.
˝We knew that if we left any bugs in the game, it would immediately result in a bullet in the skull. The next opportunity should not come. Thatˊs why we filed the details again, again, again. We are working to remove any retardation that provides a reason to leave the game. ˝
The characters liked Rovia a lot. It was another game among the others, except they played it damn well. At some home parties, a test version installed on Niklas Hedˊs cell phone ended up with his boyfriendˊs girlfriend. After a couple of hours, Hed began to miss her cellphone. At first she thought the woman was polite. But that was not the question:
˝Damn this is addictive,ˊthe woman said. ˝Can I go on anyway?ˊ
˝Just give that phone back now, ˝her boyfriend acknowledged.
An ordinary young woman got stuck in a mobile game and only got out of it when she had to. It was a tough thing. Niklas Hed knew that Rovio had found the material for the hit.
Angry Birds was released in December 2009 and became number one in the United States in May 2010. That spring, Rovio introduced Angry Birds at the Game Connect event and built a small show featuring bird style. Niklas Hedˊs email was filled shortly after the event with inquiries and orders.
˝Everyone realized what it was about. Now the fuck is running! ˝
+
Rovioˊs boys and girls are still running hard. They got some head start because of the difficulty of programming graphics for mobile games. Niklas Hed says they havenˊt stopped yet to celebrate properly. They are not yet on target.
Get Keep. Monetize without selling. Crust. Hold. Money for unsold.

Thatˊs where Rovioˊs hard values are, and this is just the beginning. The vision of Hed and partners is to provide ˝great quality experiences for fans around the world.˝ If they do well, they can become the worldˊs largest entertainment brand, bigger than Disney. But thatˊs a potential consequence, not an official goal.
˝You have to put the bar as high as possible,˝ Hed says, pressing the chair with the armrests and folding the knees down on the chair.
˝I donˊt have time to flaunt that we are becoming a little bigger than the Moomin. I donˊt belittle the Moomins at all - they have a great story - but we have different goals.˝
Hed believes Rovio has a lot to offer. However, the pressures are high. The cynics suspect that the stunt drug will cool down, and then there will be no more play. Or that Rovioˊs Finns canˊt succeed and sell off their company in an emergency as soon as the first breakthrough comes. Now it would make many billions.
Niklas Hed rejects such concerns. If it had, Rovio would have been sold five times already.
˝The pressures are intense, but in the direction of the fans and not the cynics. But of course we also want to show them the eggs.˝
The sale was negotiated when Rovio was smaller. The other parties to the discussions were much bigger. However, it was revealed at meetings that an alliance with big companies would slow down Rovio. Someone else would write the rules.
The Heds realized that it would be difficult to create conditions in the new pattern where they could continue to do the same thing with the same high spirits as before. They recognized this: we are selfish bastards. What is most important? Neat to do. What could be cooler than this? Hardly anything. Or what would Niklas Hed do with ten bucks when he could get twenty bucks in the future? Or two if things go wrong. That would be more than he ever needed.
Independence does not eliminate the concerns of the companyˊs owners, of course.
Niklas Hed is particularly concerned about whether Rovio can maintain his entrepreneurial character as he grows up. In the future, he would like to create a new game that would be a five star experience and as hard a hit as Angry Birds. Another dream is to develop an edu application to support learning, which would be a revolutionary case in terms of entertaining and addictive.
˝Itˊs like a time machine. Two hours went by, damn it - is it time for food already?˝
Finding the best entertaining educational material in the world is even more challenging than building a good game. Hed has many other interesting ideas. He sees weaknesses in services like Netflix, YouTube and Facebook. Everything is possible. Some Finn may still be attacking them.
+
Finland is a good base for Rovio.
Combining technology, entertainment and marketing is a difficult one. However, Niklas Hed has seen that a team managed by the Finns knows it. In addition to Hedie, names such as Tuomas Erikoinen, Jaakko Iisalo, Tuomo Lehtinen, Raine Mäki, Ari Pulkkinen and Miika Virtanen deserve the highest honor.
˝Finns are raised in creative thinking,˝ says Niklas Hed. ˝The Chinese have been educated to not think. On the mobile games side, weˊre a bit like six Swedes.˝

Education is a great asset. A good example of the power of education is Kajaani, who had to die in misery when she lost her paper mill. However, Kainuuˊs quiet missions started to increase the game-players and the results have been promising. Even darkness may have turned to our advantage. Young people squeak indoors for entertainment because itˊs cold and dark outside. They have a creative imagination because they read a lot.
Many small businesses are now emerging in the gaming industry. The sector already employs nearly 2,500 Finns, as many as one large listed company. Niklas Hed believes that games and other application development will become like the new Nokia, which is so much needed here.
˝However, it is not created by one giant company but is split up into a few big companies and many smaller ones.˝
Hed predicts that after ten years in the gaming business, the number of Finns earning their living has quadrupled. Including developers of other digital services, the population can hopefully grow to 50,000.
Nokia never employed so many Finns.


         "
    </string>
</resources>